this is the simplest kind of circular
motion
and it's where you have a constant
angular speed constant angular speed
right
now we're going to need to draw a new
diagram without people on it so draw me
a circle
okay roughly
and
we're going to think about this circular
motion okay so
i actually we're going to do some
constructions off of this okay and for
that reason you need to make your
drawing fairly accurate which is why i
got all the equipment out okay
significantly i want to ask you a couple
of things
firstly
this linear velocity right
if we're talking about uniform circular
motion
where the angular speed angle velocity
is constant so we're going around at a
constant
rate okay so we're making laps
consistently we're not speeding i'm not
slowing down okay
a constant here a constant omega is
going to imply a constant linear
velocity because r is a constant omega
constant whole thing's constant okay so
therefore if these two things are going
to go sort of complex numbers on you
right if these two lines represent
the velocity if they represent vectors
right it's got a direction that's why
i've got an arrow on there but this
length is important okay these lengths
in fact because it's constant they
should be the same okay so what however
big your circle is you know on mine one
of
these something like 20 centimeters
sorry
25. whatever they are i want them to be
the same on your diagram it doesn't seem
like it's going to be that important but
it will be okay
now i don't know if you've noticed i've
been a bit
funny with my language
i want to talk about this velocity okay
now we've already established that the
linear speed is constant
but
is
the linear velocity constant
it's my question
is the linear velocity
constant
now don't forget just to refresh your
memory right we've got two different
kinds of quantities in this in this
world that's 2d okay we've got scalars
and we've got vectors do you remember
what they mean what does it mean for
something to be scalar
it's just a value with a magnitude it's
just the size right so you can add up
scalar numbers together there's you know
like three and five they're scalars and
you get eight okay
but a vector makes it more complex not
only does it have a magnitude
but as we've been mentioning it has a
direction right so it's it's a scalar
right
plus another scalar
namely magnitude and direction so it's
got two values to it two parts and so
you know under complex numbers we talked
about the real part and the imaginary
part right
in this case we've got direction now can
you see
as you go around the circle
direction is constantly changing
you see that direction is constantly
changing at every different point let's
name them say p1 versus p2 okay
the velocity is changing because the
direction is changing the magnitude is
the same
right you've got the magnitude but the
direction
is not the same okay
so that means from this velocity to this
velocity there's a change right it's a
change in velocity
we have a name for that don't we
change in velocity what's that called
that's acceleration
so there's some acceleration in this
picture okay my question is where is the
acceleration going
now let's have a look at this okay
let me just walk you through that just
in case you lost me there's a change in
velocity right
so step one i notice there's a change in
velocity
so step two i then conclude
therefore there must be acceleration
so then my question is where
what direction is it going in and then
i'm going to go toward the language of
forces i get two forces from
acceleration okay
all right now here's where the scale of
your diagram is going to be very very
important okay am i gonna have enough
space over there probably not i'm gonna
do it over here
um you've got your scale there you're
gonna need to draw some parallel lines
as well how do you work out acceleration
acceleration is change in velocity right
so for example
if i was traveling
at one point let's see let's start from
this side i was starting my journey and
i was traveling at 10 kilometers an hour
right and then by the end of my journey
i'm traveling at 30 kilometers an hour
10 kilometers an hour
30 kilometers now
how much have i accelerated
it's not a complicated question
i've accelerated
20 kilometers per hour right that's the
that's the net the resultant
acceleration okay so the way you got
that is you take the difference you just
do final speed final velocity minus
initial velocity and that's your
acceleration does that make sense so
obviously if i was just you know doing
the inertia thing and going 10
kilometers per hour
and 10 kilometers hour just uniform
straight line motion there's no
acceleration there right no force is
acting or at least no resultant forces
okay
so therefore let's take that
understanding and bring it over here
okay velocity
velocity
okay that's change in
sorry
acceleration that's what i'm trying to
work out
it's change in velocity
that's dv on dt
okay in this case i'm just picking two
particular points in time right
here's my final velocity and here's my
initial velocity just like here's my
final velocity and here's my initial
velocity so i'm going to say well this
is v2 minus v1
right in this case i got 20 kilometers
per hour in this case we've got zero
kilometers per hour what am i going to
get
here
now here's where you've got to be super
super careful okay
i'm going to try as best i can to
represent this on the board okay i
actually want you to draw
the vectors okay so if you can make your
lines parallel to preserve the direction
of each might look roughly like this
accept it for me okay final velocity
minus
initial velocity okay
no that's way too fast
okay that'll have to do right you can do
a much better job with me because you've
got like rulers and stuff you kind of
measure all that but they go
one vector and its velocity minus the
other one okay i might even label
there's b1
and there's
v2
now one of the things you may remember
from complex numbers is that when you
are subtracting vectors
subtracting vectors is the same as
adding
a negative vector in fact that's the
same in just like normal numbers right
like like
uh
30 minus 10
that's the same as
30 plus
negative 10 right so all i need to do to
work out what this is is to well i'll do
the first vector the same
so
there's v2
and now instead of subtracting this i'm
going to add now what would it mean for
this vector to be
negative
it means the um the line's the same
right it's still going to look like this
but because negative it's going in the
opposite direction
right that's that's the negative v1 if
you like okay now the reason why this is
useful to us is because when you add
vectors you just do one
and then you do the other right that's
all you have to do to add vectors
together so that's why i've got this
space over here
okay
let's put these together right something
like this
so there are my two vectors put together
which means that the the net result is
this
that's what the um that's what the
change in velocity is when you put the
vectors together and that distance and
the direction are crucial
they're based on these distances in
these directions okay now let's take
that vector and let's put it into the
picture okay because it's an average of
these two right i'm going to join these
up and get the midpoint looks like this
okay
now if you've done it well you take the
midpoint between those two positions and
you have a look at what direction that's
going in
it should be heading
right back toward the center at least if
you've drawn it accurately okay and we
have a um we have a word for this
where it's toward the center and our
fancy
long syllable word for this is
it's
centripetal right
aiming toward the center that's where
we're going
now i don't know how you feel about that
argument
um i i think it's quite kind of nice
like it's visual right but you know us
we're mathematicians so we want
something a little more rigorous than
this okay so here's what it looks like
visually
but we're going to need to do it
algebraically as well