all right now let's just take a breath
do you remember back to when you were
first given questions like this
um something like this i don't know um x
squared minus x
something like that okay now when you
first met rational functions like this
and had to learn how to graph them and
when you learn calculus
you were so unfamiliar with these and
there were so many steps for like
intercepts vertical asymptotes
horizontal or oblique or whatever
stationary points there was like 15
things you had to learn okay and so in
order to do this well you kind of had to
you had to develop an algorithm oh i'm
going to do this and then this and then
this and this and so for instance the
way that i do it this is my um
i've had longer to think about this one
so i have a nice easy mnemonic for this
you factorize first
right then you work out what your
asymptotes are which are just your x and
y's you work that out from domain and
from the extremities then you work out
your intercepts and then you
use the factors to shade your regions
and say i'm positive negative blah blah
blah anyway okay
now now if i gave you that question
you'd be fine with it because you've
been doing it for so long but all of
this stuff is fresh okay so i'm gonna
give you a um an algorithm for going
through circular motion questions okay
now
i tried and failed to come up with a
nice mnemonic i had no vowels so if you
can come up with alternative letters for
what i'm about to tell you then um
you're more than welcome and i'd love to
find out
but um there are basically there are
four things you've got to tick off
and then you can work on habits okay so
no prizes
from me for working out what's the first
one
drawer diving thank you
now the important thing about the
diagram is it's got to have all the
forces on it the forces are the
important thing because as we go further
down
the force equations you've got what
you're going to need to work with okay
um importantly
like i said before
don't put on mr omega squared it's the
sum of all the resulting forces that are
set heading back toward the center of
motion okay but it's not an actual
physical force like tension or gravity
or or the reaction force off the table
those kinds of things
so draw a diagram right draw all the
forces on it but don't draw m r omega
squared okay because it's the sum of
forces
the second thing you got to do is once
you draw your big fancy diagram okay you
use a combination of whatever trig
and geometry you need
to work out now here's the thing right
this diagram it's all about the forces
okay
the trigger in the geometry is to work
out now where are those forces pointed
what angles right and how big are those
forces okay what are the magnitude of
those forces so you use trig and
geometry to work that out okay you might
be able to guess what three is
when you've got all of those forces in
real wacky directions you should resolve
them
okay
almost now
you you resolve it into the two
different components right namely um
horizontal
right
okay
now once you have those you add them all
up you've got all of your horizontal
forces they should add up to mr omega
squared but all your vertical forces
whatever they are
um usually by the way
you've got mr omega squared here and if
it's uniform circular motion then the
vertical forces should add up to
zero
okay
final step and this is the hard part
based on whatever question they're
asking you
you have to solve the force equations
okay you have a couple of them
work out what they're trying to ask you
and then fit in all your information
diagram
whatever geometry you need resolve out
all the forces after you've worked out
the directions
and then solve