this was you know i know it's not a
conical pendulum but we're still going
through the same kinds of things we have
drawn a diagram right i've put on the
physical forces that are there
what do i do next
i did step one was to draw step two is
trig and geometry so that i can work out
like this thing when i get towards
resolving its forces which way is
everything facing okay so what i'm going
to do is i'm just going to take part of
this diagram this part where the forces
are draw that out separately so that i
can understand a little better
okay so there's the normal force right
now which way
are all of the forces and all their
magnitudes going when i start to resolve
this thing okay so if you've got some
colors there
you can see there's a horizontal
component like this
and you can see importantly that this
horizontal component of the normal force
it's centripetal it's headed towards o
so that's good that's what we want it to
do right so i'll work out what that is
in a second
and then you've got the vertical
component which is heading off like you
would expect
all right
so have a look with me
what angles can we use
in here what can we take advantage of
so there's some there's some parallel
lines there's some alternate angles if
you do your work i'm pretty sure you
should find you know up here you'll have
theta alternate angles and because this
is the normal right that means that
these two are complementary so i've got
90 minus theta there is that all right
90 minus theta 90 that means that theta
is up in this corner
okay by the same alternate angles you
can see theta will be over here okay and
that's all you need to work out what the
magnitudes of all the forces are okay
for instance the vertical one right
you've got adjacent and you've got
hypotenuse we've seen this a few times
before right starting to get the hang of
it this is clearly going to be n plus
theta
right
and conversely you'll have n sine theta
in the horizontal direction
so now i've resolved everything now i
can put it in terms of vertical and
horizontal and say well vertically i
don't want to be going up and down but
horizontally i'm going in this circle
right so
vertically
you've got n cos theta going up and
you've got mg going down right and those
should be equal to each other right so
n cos theta equals mg
nothing too dramatic there what's
happening horizontally
you've only got a single force acting
horizontally at the moment anyway okay
so you've got n sine theta and it's
going towards the center so that should
be equal to now
we're used to writing mr omega squared
first right but being that this is bank
tracks and we're kind of thinking more
about cars right we don't see we're not
usually driving around like oh wow i'm
taking this corner at you know pi on
three radians per second so probably
rather than mr omega squared we'll do m
v squared on r okay i think that that
makes more sense
okay because we will know linear
velocity
now this is in an
ideal world okay we're going around and
the only forces acting are exactly
balancing each other out you'll see
shortly what happens when that is not
the case okay
but i want to work out well what is that
speed at which i should take this corner
okay
so how am i going to work this out i've
got v squared there that's what i want
to work out okay so if i call this one
and call this
two
which way should i go and what should i
do should i add subtract
any takers
what's the cleanest way to get to v
squared and a nice simple sort of
equation just for v squared and then
hence v
i think we should divide shouldn't we
right because that'll get rid of the
ends it'll get rid of the m's
uh and you can if you do it this way
you'll just get 10 figure right which
will be useful for its own thing okay so
if i divide so i should have said 2
divided by 1. ends will cancel you'll
just get that m's will also cancel what
am i going to get v squared on g
r
alright
so now if i just rearrange this a little
bit v squared equals g r tan theta okay
put a box around that
put a box around this because
what this tells you is the optimum speed
to take this turn this is the optimum or
velocity speed it's all squared so it
doesn't matter in this case okay
this is the optimus p given the radius
of the road
or the curve of the road and whatever
angle you're in banked at
now that's fine that's good um but
that's sort of assuming the road's
already there like it has a given radius
it's going to go that far and you can
measure how the angle is right if i were
a road designer okay i actually am in
the position where i get to decide what
these are
based on this right so i'm looking at
this from a very different point of view
okay i'm making the road and i'm
thinking hmm how far should i embank
this okay
because i can you know i can put
whatever amount of dirt and concrete and
stuff to make this kind of height okay
so how will i do this it's a bit of a
fancy algebraic trick
remember i told you um
this diagram is actually way off scale
right
this angle theta is not really going to
be that high and when you think about it
like
you think about the roads that you've
traveled on and if you've been on a
highway
and you've seen terms like this they'll
be very very gentle inclines right in
order to take these curves okay so in
other words you have small values of
theta
okay
now one of the things that you might
remember from when you first did the
trigonometry of um sorry the calculus of
trigonometric functions right
is that tan theta right and sine theta
are very close together for small values
of theta right because they look like
i'll just use this empty space
here's sine and then here is tan and
then well it's gone too far
there's that asymptote of pi on two
right so in here they're pretty much the
same thing or the difference between
them is negligible okay so i can say
sine theta is going to be roughly equal
to
tan theta
is that right
okay now what i'm going to do is i'm
going to substitute that into this line
maybe i'll call this three so i can do
this okay so i'm going to sub into
three okay
so instead of tan theta over here i'm
going to say that's sine theta and it's
roughly equal to v squared on gr
close enough okay and the reason why
this is useful the reason why i would go
to sine theta is because i know what
sine theta is in terms of
these distances here right
this hypotenuse is d and this opposite
side to the angle is h that's what i'm
trying to find right so this is really
equal to opposite on hypotenuse so yeah
okay now i find the road designer and i
want to work out how high should i make
this embankment right i just have to
multiply d across
and then look at what we've got here
okay
before we had optimum speed that's
that's if you the road's already there
and it already has a given radius at a
given angle okay but if you're in the
opposite position you're like i can
decide what i want the road to be then
this line
will give you the optimum
height
of the embankment okay now notice what
it depends on
it depends on let's go from the bottom
it depends on r right that's that's the
radius of this row that's probably going
to be decided for you right the council
is like look this is where the road has
to go so they they provide that to you
depends on gravity constant depends on d
what was d again
that's that's the road width isn't it
again that's decided for you say okay
well look we need three lanes for this
highway or it's one lane or whatever
okay
now the final piece is v-square right so
it's like look if you know
where your road has to be how wide you
know gravity and then if you know
a required speed or if you want a
particular optimum speed like say oh i
don't know
a speed limit
right you say look this is on a highway
people should be taking this curve at
110 kilometers per hour right instead of
being in this position where you're the
driver and you're like how fast should i
go you're in this position you say look
i know how fast they should go and so
i'm going to substitute that into here
and get a height out does that make
sense
okay
so this is all in an ideal world
where everything is optimized and
everything is nice and perfect right
optimum speed optimum height for
everything
but we don't live in an ideal world do
we
people take corners at all different
speeds
people have cars of all different masses
okay so what's going to happen is for
instance you know um suppose this is
this corner here right and i'm just a
little bit more reckless than you so i'm
like okay speed limit's 110 i just go
ahead and i take it 110. but everyone
else all the normal people they're like
look at the how tight that curve is
right so people come in and they slow
down they approach it maybe 90
kilometers an hour okay
uh or maybe you have like a really heavy
car okay so when you have a heavy car
there's going to be more forces acting
this direction in this direction right
and i've got a light car so it's going
to go so we have to account for all of
these things okay
so this is an ideal world
you can rule all that off we're going to
draw a new diagram for a
non-ideal world okay and i need more
space